<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Abouts on Yanfei Wu</title>
    <link>/about/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Abouts on Yanfei Wu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy;2016 Yanfei Wu</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 21:48:51 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, and welcome to my site. My name is Yanfei Wu. I obtained my PhD degree in Materials Science and Engineering from University of Minnesota. My PhD research focused on investigating the structure and properties of novel organic electronic materials. By analyzing a large amount of data collected with a number of advanced characterization techniques, I was able to generate some insights into the fundamental structure-property correlations to help solve the challenging problems in materials application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fascinated by how data-driven analytics applications are transforming our world, I decided to pivot into Data Science. Through persistent self-education (taking a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;https://yanfei-wu.github.io/course/&#34;&gt;MOOCs&lt;/a&gt; and working on &lt;a href=&#34;https://yanfei-wu.github.io/project/&#34;&gt;personal projects&lt;/a&gt;), I have acquired diverse skills in statistical analysis, data visualization, and machine learning. I&amp;rsquo;ve also started to branch out to learn more about Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence. The more I learn, the more curious I get. I find myself sincerely enjoy &lt;strong&gt;becoming&lt;/strong&gt; a data scientist. I think this is one of the things that really attract me about this field: the opportunity to learn something new every day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>